<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section 
	PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd"
>
<section>

	<title>Overview of the GeneSEZ approach</title>

	<para>
		An MDSD platform based on the GeneSEZ meta-model was created. A
		schematic representation of this is shown in
		<xref linkend="de.genesez.intro.overview" />
		.
	</para>

	<figure id="de.genesez.intro.overview">

		<title>Schematic overview of the GeneSEZ approach</title>

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="html">
				<imagedata align="center"
					fileref="de.genesez.intro.overview.png" />
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="fo">
				<imagedata align="center"
					fileref="core/intro/de.genesez.intro.overview.png" scalefit="1"
					width="100%" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>Following concepts are characteristic for the main component:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				The
				<emphasis>GeneSEZ Core Meta-Model</emphasis>
				as central component,
				which provides information for source code
				generation in a preprocessed form and is used for model
				transformation.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				<emphasis>Model-adapters</emphasis>
				are used to create GeneSEZ models with information from the
				application models.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				The
				<emphasis>GeneSEZ components</emphasis>
				as function libraries and common basis for generation of source code
				in different programming languages.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				The
				<emphasis>platform-projects</emphasis>
				provide source code templates for the
				respective programming language
				together with libraries and
				frameworks for the source code
				generation.
			</para>

		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		The application models can be created and elaborated regardless
		of the MDSD-platform. With model-adapters the relevant data for source
		code generation will be extracted from the application models and then
		transformed into GeneSEZ-models.
		Based on this GeneSEZ-model more model
		transformations can be done until a model-to-text transformation for
		source code generation is performed and the source code artifacts are
		generated automatically.
		In most cases complete source code cannot be
		generated in a manner that makes sense. Therefore the source code must
		be completed with manual implementation.
	</para>

	<para>
		Its not necessary to do these steps in these order. After a first
		version of an application model is available, it can be transformed
		into a GeneSEZ model and thereafter the source code can be generated.
		This source code can be extended with manual implementation.
		While the
		application model is still elaborated, it can frequently be
		transformed into source code where the manual implementations will
		remain.
		This iterative procedure allows backflow of information that
		arise from implementation to the application modeling. There these
		information can be used to enhance the application model.
	</para>

	<para>
		A significant advantage in the development of model
		transformations is the possibility to print the GeneSEZ meta-model
		complete on two DIN-A4 sites and use them as an overview on how
		specific information can be accessed.
	</para>

</section>