<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section 
	PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd"
>
<section>
	<title>Idea of the GeneSEZ approach</title>


	<para>
		In the MDA/MDSD approach for software engineering, created
		application
		models will be automatically transformed into source code
		through
		model-transformations. Therefore an MDSD platform supports
		following model-transformations:
	</para>

	<variablelist>

		<varlistentry>

			<term>
				<emphasis role="bold">Model-to-model
					transformations
				</emphasis>
			</term>

			<listitem>

				<para>
					Used to create new models with the opportunity to use
					different modeling languages as source and as destination.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>

			<term>
				<emphasis role="bold">Model modifications</emphasis>
			</term>

			<listitem>

				<para>
					Changes a model mostly to change or append information.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

		<varlistentry>

			<term>
				<emphasis role="bold">Model-to-text
					transformations
				</emphasis>
			</term>

			<listitem>

				<para>
					Used to generate source code and other used files for a
					software.
				</para>

			</listitem>

		</varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

	<para>
		Model-to-model transformations and model modifications ensure the
		preparation of models, while model-to-text transformations do the
		source code generation of a software. The transformation target is
		mostly an
		object-oriented programming language.
	</para>

	<para>
		The similar the concepts of the programming language and the
		modeling language are, the easier the creation of
		model
		transformations, that maps both concepts. Furthermore the
		model
		transformations become more intuitive and maintainable in this
		way.
	</para>

	<para>
		In the field of modeling languages for MDSD-platforms
		UML and DSLs
		are widely-used. The UML provides object-oriented modeling
		concepts and
		has the right level of abstraction for the source code
		generation.
		Unfortunately, due to the increasing amount of modeling
		concepts, the
		UML became inapplicable as modeling language for
		model transformations:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>

		<listitem>

			<para>it became very complex</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				it contains information that are not needed for source code
				generation.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				there is no overview of the UML meta-model in which you can see
				how the information can be accessed.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				it contains information of graphical representation of model
				elements, e. g. pictures of stereotypes.
			</para>

		</listitem>

		<listitem>

			<para>
				many approaches show that only parts of the UML are useful for
				MDA/MDSD platforms (e. g. Stephen J.
				Mellor and
				Marc Balcer.
				Executable UML: A Foundation for Model-Driven
				Architectures.
				Addison-Wesley Longman Publishing Co., Inc.,
				Boston,
				MA, USA, 2002.
				Foreword by Ivar Jacoboson. und Paul
				Baker, Zhen Ru
				Dai, Jens
				Grabowski, Øystein Haugen, Ina
				Schieferdecker, and Clay
				Williams.
				Model-Driven Testing: Using
				the UML Testing Profile.
				Springer-Verlag
				New York, Inc.,
				Secaucus, NJ, USA, 2007.)
			</para>

		</listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		Due to the complexity and normalized structure of the meta-model,
		the UML is relatively inapplicable for model transformations.
		Also the
		fact, that the UML specification does not provide an overview over the
		meta-model, makes things even worse.
	</para>

	<para>
		Besides the UML there are DSLs. DSLs use concepts of an
		application area or
		technical aspects for description of models.
		Thereby the functional
		DSLs are more interesting, because the models
		can be discussed with
		experts of the scope.
		However such modeling
		languages increase the mismatch between modeling concept and concept
		of the programming language. With this it comes to more
		complex and
		application specific model transformations.
		In the perspective of
		transformation this leads to ongoing creation of model transformations
		for the same programming language with different modeling languages.
	</para>

	<para>
		Based on the consequences that comes with the usage of UML or
		DSLs, the idea of GeneSEZ was not to directly evaluate the
		meta-models,
		with which the models were created, but instead to create
		a separate meta-model for an MDSD-platform and evaluate it.
		Its
		structure should be suitable for evaluation with model transformations
		and should only contain information that are useful for the source
		code generation.
		This leads to a meta-model, that is especially
		suitable for the last model transformation steps in source code
		generation.
		For the MDSD-platform this means a stable, reusable and
		investment save base for source code generation.
	</para>

	<para>
		With the terms of MDA the GeneSEZ meta-model can be classified as an
		<emphasis>abstracting mapping</emphasis>
		, because many information from the UML are unnecessary for the source
		code generation.
		With the concepts of DSLs it can be called a DSL for
		model transformations, especially for model-to-text transformations.
		Relating to UML it indicates a simplier and scarcer meta-model for
		model transformations.
		Relating to functional DSLs an intermediate step
		is introduced in the model transformations, which transforms the
		application specific meta-model into the GeneSEZ meta-model and
		in the
		next step the GeneSEZ meta-model will be transformed into
		source code.
		Complex transformations into source code can be avoided and the model
		transformations from the GeneSEZ meta-model into source code can be
		reused in different areas of application.
	</para>

</section>